Leopold von Ranke Papers
Leopold von Ranke Papers
- Y Series
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, 24 March 1850; Y240 (Box 4)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, 10 May 1850; Y241 (Box 4)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, 26 April 1850; Y242 (Box 4)
  - John T. Graves to his mother, 4 November 1845; Y243 (Box 4)
  - John T. Graves and Helena Graves, 22 and 26 March 1846; Y244 (Box 4)
  - John T. Graves and Helena Graves to Clara Ranke, 26 March 1848; Y245 (Box 4)
  - John T. Graves to Leopold Ranke, 23 July 1848; Y246 (Box 4)
  - John T. Graves to Clara Ranke, 27 Ju1y 1849; Y247 (Box 4)
  - John T. Graves to Clara Ranke, 2 November 1849; Y248 (Box 4)
  - John T. Graves to Clara Ranke, 28 January 1850; Y249 (Box 4)
  - John T. Graves to Clara Ranke, 30 January 1850; Y250 (Box 4)
  - John T. Graves to Leopold Ranke, 3 February 1850; Y251 (Box 4)
  - John T. Graves to Leopold Ranke, 2 March 1850; Y252 (Box 4)
  - John T. Graves to Clara Ranke, 11 April 1850; Y253 (Box 4)
  - Amelia Graves to Clara Ranke, 13 August [no year], Y254 (Box 4)
  - Amelia Graves to Clara Ranke, undated; Y255 (Box 4)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, 7 May 1850; Y256 (Box 4)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, 9 April 1850; Y257 (Box 4)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, 4 May 1850; Y258 (Box 4)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr (?) to Clara Ranke, undated; Y259 (Box 4)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr (?) to Clara Ranke (?), undated; Y260 (Box 4)
  - Amelia Graves (?) to Clara Ranke, undated; Y261 (Box 4)
  - Hamit S. Miller to Clara Ranke, 24 November 1851; Y262 (Box 4)
  - Hamit S. Miller to Clara Ranke, 30 November 1850; Y263 (Box 4)
  - Mary L. Hemans to Clara Ranke, 23 March [no year], Y264 (Box 4)
  - Mary L. Hemans to Clara Ranke, 3 October [no year], Y265 (Box 4)
  - Author unknown to Clara Ranke, 28 January 185?; Y266 (Box 4)
  - Fanny Prite to Clara Ranke, 6 September [no year], Y267 (Box 4)
  - Civilia Kingard to Clara Ranke, 8 November 1852; Y268 (Box 4)
  - Fanny Prite to Clara Ranke, 18 October [no year], Y269 (Box 4)
  - Marfils von Wallchranz (?) to Clara Ranke (?), written on a devotional print of "Marienbads Heilquelle", 23 December 1852; Y270 (Box 4)
  - Mary L. Carman to Clara Ranke, 10 September or December 1852; Y271 (Box 4)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr (?) to Clara Ranke, undated; Y272 (Box 4)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, 17 January 1851; Y273 (Box 4)
  - Mara Matilda Twining to Clara Ranke, 5 October [no year], Y274 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified author to Leopold Ranke, 27 January 1851; Y275 (Box 4)
  - ? von Preussen to Leopold Ranke, 10 November 1852; Y276 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified author to Leopold Ranke, 14 March 1852; Y277 (Box 4)
  - ? Tempelhoff to Clara Ranke, 1850; Y278 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified author to Clara Ranke, 1 October 1852; Y279 (Box 4)
  - Lina Boehm to Clara Ranke, undated; Y280 (Box 4)
  - ? Han to Clara Ranke, 11 March 1852; Y281 (Box 4)
  - Lina Boehm to Clara Ranke, undated; Y282 (Box 4)
  - G. Willoghby Hemans to Clara Ranke, 12 April 1852; Y283 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified author, Y284 (Box 4)
  - Lina Boehm to Clara Ranke (?), undated; Y285 (Box 4)
  - Mara Matilda Twining to Clara Ranke, 2 July 1852; Y286 (Box 4)
  - Lina Boehm to Clara Ranke, undated; Y287 (Box 4)
  - Lina Boehm to Clara Ranke, undated; Y288 (Box 4)
  - "Aunt Annie" to Clara Ranke, 6 December 1851; Y289 (Box 4)
  - Harriett M. Owen to Helena Graves (?), 3 June [no year], Y290 (Box 4)
  - John T. Graves to Leopold Ranke, 23 July 1850; Y291 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified author to Clara Ranke, undated; Y292 (Box 4)
  - Elizabeth Lutheran Johnson to Clara Ranke, March 1848; Y293 (Box 4)
  - Mary Mohl to Clara Ranke, 22 August [no year], Y294 (Box 4)
  - Katherina Wallace to Clara Ranke, 1 December 1851; Y295 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified author to Clara Ranke, 15 July 1850; Y296 (Box 4)
  - Hamit S. Miller to Clara Ranke, 1 December 1851; Y297 (Box 4)
  - Hamit S. Miller to Clara Ranke, undated; Y298 (Box 4)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, undated; Y299 (Box 4)
  - Louisa Hay Kerr to Clara Ranke, 15 November 1850; Y300 (Box 4)
  - Hingen P. Sobelling to Clara Ranke, undated; Y301 (Box 4)
  - Sidney Broing to Clara Ranke, undated; Y302 (Box 4)
  - Mary Mohl to Clara Ranke, 22 January [no year], 11 July [no year], 8 April [no year], Y303-305 (Box 4)
  - Rosine von Wintgen to Clara Ranke, 20 July 1852; Y306 (Box 4)
  - A.S. Smyth to Clara Ranke, 12 October [no year], Y307 (Box 4)
  - A.S. Perceval to Clara Ranke, 3 June 1850; Y308 (Box 4)
  - Hermann Pertr to Clara Ranke, undated; Y309 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified author to Clara Ranke, 31 July [no year], Y310 (Box 4)
  - Marfils von Wallchranz (?) to Clara Ranke, written on a devotional print of "Marienbads Heilquelle", 15 November 1852; Y311 (Box 4)
  - Mara Matilda Twining to Clara Ranke, 1 January 1853; Y312 (Box 4)
  - Lina Boehm to Clara Ranke, undated; Y313 (Box 4)
  - Lina Boehm to Clara Ranke, undated; Y314 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified author to Louise Haberland, 4 April 1850; Y315 (Box 4)
  - Note citing Crabbe Robinson's recollections of Wordsworth, Y316 (Box 4)
  - Unidentified author to Clara Ranke, undated; Y317 (Box 4)
  - Clara Ranke to unidentified recipient, undated; Y318 (Box 4)
  - L. Zimmermann to Clara Ranke, 26 May 1850; Y319 (Box 4)
  - Berlin police certificate, 5 January 1853; Y320 (Box 4)
- GMC Series
  - Siegfried Hirsch, lecture notes for courses in Staatsgeschichte and Kirchengeschichte at the Prussian War College, schedules of courses, class rolls, German and French newspaper clippings, 1848; 1851-1853,; undated; GMC537-538; 13 folders (Box 5)
  - Siegfried Hirsch, lecture notes for courses in Staatsgeschichte and Kirchengeschichte at the Prussian War College, schedules of courses, class rolls, German and French newspaper clippings, 1848; 1851-1853,; undated; GMC537-538; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Ranke's passport, GMC539 (Package 1)
  - Theodor Wiedemann, Descriptive evaluation of the Ranke Library
    - Original manuscript pages, GMC540 (Box 7)
      Restricted due to fragile condition. Researchers should use either the microfilm version of this item, or one of the two photocopies (GMC541 or GMC542, also in Box 7), NOT the originals.
    - Photocopy, bound, GMC541; 1 volume (Box 7)
    - Photocopy, unbound, GMC542 (Box 7)
  - Theodor Wiedemann, Catalogue of the manuscripts in the Ranke library, GMC544 (Box 7)
  - Theodor Wiedermann, Supplements to the catalogue of the manuscripts in the Ranke library, GMC545 (Box 7)
  - Theodor Wiedemann, Catalogue of the collections of manuscripts from which Ranke had copies made, bound volume, GMC546 (Box 7)
  - Theodor Wiedemann, Catalogue of some works used by Weidemann in making his abstracts, bound volume, GMC547 (Box 8)
  - Albert, Prince of Prussia, to Leopold Ranke, 24 May 1886; GMC548 (Box 8)
  - Königlich General Ordens pour le Merite Kommission to Leopold Ranke, 23 April 1875; GMC549 (Box 8)
  - Königlich Preussischen Ordens, list of awards of honor, May 1874; GMC550 (Box 8)
  - Wilhelm Maurenbrecher to Leopold Ranke, 11 November 1867; GMC551 (Box 8)
  - Jean Francois Boissonade to Emile Egger, undated; GMC552 (Box 8)
  - Otto Richter to Leopold Ranke, 28 January 1885; GMC553 (Box 8)
  - Ludolf Krehl to Leopold Ranke (?), 25 December 1877; GMC554 (Box 8)
  - Leopold Ranke, manuscript notes on Montesquieu's "Considerations sur les causes de 1a grandeur des Romains et de leur decadence", GMC555 (Box 8)
  - Leopold Ranke, manuscript notes on Christophe Coudrette's "Histoire generale...de la Compagnie de Jesus..., cf. Ra 271.5 C85, GMC556 (Box 8)
  - Wilhelm von Doenniges to Leopold Ranke, 19 August 1854+; GMC557 (Box 8)
  - Leopold Ranke, miscellaneous trivia: envelopes, visiting cards, announcements, invitations (18 items), GMC558 (Box 8)
  - ? von Doeninz to Leopold Ranke, 23 May 1866; GMC559 (Box 8)
  - Lazar Assenitwitz to Leopold Ranke, 22 February 1849; GMC560 (Box 8)
  - D.P. Carhel (?) to Leopold Ranke, 25 May 1866; GMC561 (Box 8)
  - Mayor of Berlin to Leopold Ranke, city budget for 1886-1887, 17 April 1886; GMC562 (Box 8)
  - Johann Eduard Wappaus to Leopold Ranke, 3 March 1848; GMC563 (Box 8)
  - Ulrich Lianbauant to Leopold Ranke, 18 March 1866; GMC564 (Box 8)
  - Emmerick von Tkalac to Leopold Ranke, 27 February 1884; GMC565 (Box 8)
  - ? Tempeltrug to Leopold Ranke, 28 October 1882; GMC566 (Box 8)
  - ? von Bergmann to Leopold Ranke, 25 May 1886; GMC567 (Box 8)
  - Michael Petzoldt to Leopold Ranke, 4 May 1886; GMC568 (Box 8)
  - G.A. Schönrich, song "Dankt dem Herrn jauchzt volle Chore," composed in honor of Ranke's 90th birthday and as a Christmas gift, 1885; GMC569 (Box 8)
  - Paul Frohwein to Leopold Ranke, 14 March 1886; GMC570 (Box 8)
  - Ambassador of the Duchy of Württemberg to an unidentified member of the Ranke family, 1886; GMC571 (Box 8)
  - Magistrat of Berlin to Leopold Ranke, letter of transmittal, 24 January 1854; GMC572 (Box 8)
  - Magistrat of Berlin to Leopold Ranke, encloses a census report, 14 November 1885; GMC573 (Box 8)
  - House Marshall of the King of Prussia to Leopold Ranke, a protocol of directions for attendance at royal balls, 14 February and 21 February 1886; GMC574 (Box 8)
  - Emil Kuhn to Leopold Ranke, 10 May 1878; GMC575 (Box 8)
  - Ernst Ranke to Leopold Ranke, 6 November 1855; GMC576 (Box 8)
  - List of names for mailing announcements of death of Leopold Ranke, 1886; GMC577 (Box 8)
  - Death notice of Leopold Ranke, 24 May 1886; GMC578 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous trivia, GMC579; 5 items (Box 8)
  - E. von Westphalen to Leopold Ranke, undated; GMC580 (Box 8)
  - Heinrich Weiss to Leopold Ranke, 25 March 1877; GMC581 (Box 8)
  - Milan I (Milan Obrenovic), King of Serbia to Leopold Ranke, letterpress certificate conferring Order of Holy Save, 29 November 1884; GMC582 (Box 8)
  - Fritz Hummel to Leopold Ranke, 2 July 1884+; GMC583 (Box 8)
  - Friedrich Klincksieck to Leopold Ranke, 29 October 1852; GMC584 (Box 8)
  - Leopold Ranke, notes found in Wilhelm Wackernagel, Deutsches Lesebuch... (5 vols, Basel, 1836-1878), GMC585 (Box 8)
  - E. Partington to Leopold Ranke, 1885 ?; GMC586 (Box 8)
  - Leopold Ranke to Heinrich von Ranke, cf. Leopold von Ranke, Das Briefwerk, edited by Walther P. Fuchs (Hamburg, 1949), pp. 186-87, 7 April 1829; GMC587 (Box 8)
  - Konstantin Höhlbaum to Leopold Ranke, cf 300.A J91, 6 September 1874; GMC588 (Box 8)
  - Leopold Ranke, fragments of unidentified manuscripts (4 items), GMC589 (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous trivia, photos, and musical scores (9 pieces), GMC590 (Box 8)
  - Leopold Ranke, glosses and notes to Frederic le Grand, Histoire de mon temps, see Ranke MS 422, GMC591 (Box 8)
  - (Heinrich) Julian Schmidt to Leopold Ranke, 19 January 1882+; GMC592 (Box 8)
  - Ernst Ranke, Festgabe zum Neunzigsten Geburstag Leopold von Ranke, pamphlet printed in Marburg, 21 December 1885; GMC593 (Box 8)
  - Clara Ranke, verses composed for her husband's birthday, 21 December 1857; GMC594 (Box 8)
  - Leopold Ranke, notebook in embroidered velvet cover, GMC595 (Box 8)
  - Friednhelm von Ranke, signed statement that all of the books of his father, Leopold, were included in the sale to Syracuse University, 22 April 1887; GMC596 (Box 8)
  - Classed catalog of books in the Ranke Library, GMC597 (Box GMC597)
    in its own oversize clamshell box
  - Friednhelm von Ranke to Herr Mayer and Herr Mueller, list of articles sent to Professor Bennett with the Ranke Library, 31 August 1887; GMC598 (Box 8)
  - Heinrich Wilhelm Werner Vildhaut to Leopold Ranke, 10 May l880; GMC599 (Box 8)
  - Leopold Ranke to Marie, Queen of Bavaria, 10 March 1864+; GMC603 (Box 8)
  - Engelbert Kessler to Leopold Ranke, 10 February 1886; GMC604 (Box 8)
  - Gisbert Vincke to Leopold Ranke, 8 September 1884; GMC605 (Box 8)
  - Richard Fleischer to Leopold Ranke, 4 July 1882; GMC903 (Box 8)
  - Augusta, Empress of Germany, to Leopold Ranke, 10 April 1875; GMC1080 (Box 8)
  - (Box 8)
- Z series
  - Obituary notice of death of Ranke from the Manchester Guardian, 25 May 1886; Z1 (Box 8)
  - Clara Ranke to Louisa Tiarks Ranke with a postscript by Leopold, undated; Z2 (Box 8)
  - Typescript commentary on above, Z3 (Box 8)
  - Seven autographs by Ranke, Z4 (Box 8)
  - Certified copy made 5 February 1934 of entry of marriage of Leopold Ranke and Helena Clarissa Graves, 26 October 1843; Z5 (Box 8)
  - Engagement announcement of Maximiliane Helene Ranke to Lieutenant Wilhelm von Kotze, signed by Leopold and Clara Ranke, Berlin, 2 March 1864; Z6 (Box 8)
  - Articles of agreement for marriage of Leopold Ranke and Helena Clarissa Graves, 24 October 1843; Z7 (Box 8)
  - Photograph of Ranke in his study, undated; Z8 (Box ??)
- Miscellaneous series
  - Institut impérial de France Medallion, color photocopies, MISC1 (Box 8)
  - Institut impérial de France Medallion, MISC2 (Oversize 1)
  - Lithograph portrait of Ranke, 1859; MISC3 (Oversize 1)
  - Honorary doctorate, Marburg, 1883; MISC4 (Map-case 64)
  - Citizenship certificate, Berlin, 1885; MISC5; modern color photographic reproduction, not original (Map-case 64)
  - Unidentified fragment, MISC6 (Box 8)